[Music]
the following is a production of Frankie
greatest and the internet Museum of
geography
[Music]
internet laser and holography talk show
our toll-free number is
1-800-458-3525 or you can send an email
to holotalk
poloworld.com we've got telephone calls
we've got emails we've got special
guests coming up so thank you for tuning
in and let's get this week's show on the
road
hello this is Frankie Freitas and
welcome to another broadcast of holotalk
Debbie Lee has the week off
I would like to welcome the Educators
who are listening to hollow talk from
the Eisenhower National Clearinghouse
for mathematics and science education
the hello world site is featured this
month at the Eisenhower site under the
category of Education reform in action
also thanks to all the listeners who
took the time to email and say that they
enjoy listening to the show as you can
imagine it takes a lot of work to put
this type of show together each week so
it was very nice indeed to see that it's
being enjoyed by you the listeners
we're continuing to broadcast in 14-4
for a number of different reasons number
one people still have 14-4 modems there
are quite a few 14-4 modems still out
there the second reason is basically
bandwidth conservation which I strongly
believe in you just can't keep clogging
up this internet with stuff being
transferred all the time everyone who's
listening to this can certainly
understand what it is that I'm saying I
don't need to double this file size and
deliver it over 28.8 in order for anyone
to understand what's being said you're
going to have much higher quality in the
signal itself it's going to sound more
like an FN broadcast rather than an AM
broadcast but I just can't see
transferring that much information
over the internet in the same amount of
time
however if we go to video which we would
like to do after the holidays we will
naturally have to move on to a 28 8
broadcast stream hopefully there are a
lot of 28 8 modems under the Christmas
tree this year you will also need the
Real Player 5.0 to view these shows so
if you haven't downloaded the free
player you should plan on doing so
before we change over
last week Debbie reported on a
fascinating new technology called
lightcraft we received quite a few
emails about it so we're going to take a
portion of this show to investigate this
a little further lightcraft technology
is actually a laser propulsion system
for space flight now folks this is right
out of Science Fiction the spacecraft
Rises on a beam of laser light
this is not a theory or some UFO story
from the tabloids this is reality it's
already being done
I would like to thank one of our
listeners Scott I know I don't usually
use names but I told him I'd thank him
who did some web research and sent the
URLs this week I checked them out and I
want to tell you I am hooked on
lightcraft
now I have a six second movie from White
Sands New Mexico showing this technology
at work I'm not going to give you the
URL with where to find this movie
because I want to go over what this
technology is all about before you see
it and we'll get back to this in just a
moment
if you're looking for an internet
provider that you can finally settle
down with look to Internet Internet
connect the Allentown Bethlehem and
Eastern areas along with reading
Philadelphia and Phillipsburg New Jersey
areas the whole of world site and the
holotalk show both rely on the
state-of-the-art equipment and fast
connection speed that internet to bring
you this programming and I wouldn't risk
your listening satisfaction with any
other provider if you think all internet
providers are the same you're in for a
pleasant surprise visit internet at
www.enter.net to get more information on
switching over from your current
provider
foreign
okay before we go on to our presentation
on light craft I'd like to handle a
couple email questions this week
believe it or not
I left my Zip drive somewhere last night
telephone calls that came through are on
my zip disk which is sitting right here
but I don't have a drive
to edit the telephone calls into the
show this week so we'll get to the
telephone calls next week I apologize
for that
okay let's go to an email question our
first one is this it's a strange reading
this without Debbie here
what different effects does the power
level of your laser have on the image
that you create
this was sent by a young lady I in
school and I this is a very good
question
um
the effect that it has is the fact that
the thing that you're trying to overcome
whenever you do a holographic exposure
is vibration and other things that have
an effect on the image when it's
finished
when vibration and drift creep into your
exposure
anything on that table that vibrates
more than the fraction of the wavelength
of light is going to dim that hologram
considerably
vibrates too much it's going to just get
rid of the image and you won't have
anything on the plate at all what
happens with the higher power lasers and
why they're sought after so much
is the fact that it cuts your exposure
time down now if you have a one
milliwatt laser or you have a 35
milliwatt laser obviously you're going
to find that you have a much shorter
exposure time with a 35 milliwatt than
you do the one milliwatt
hence there's less chance of something
going wrong during that time so that's
what we're looking for when we go out
there and we try and get the highest
power laser that we can for holography
is the fact that we're looking for short
exposure times and also the exposure
curve the sensitivity of the film itself
but we won't get into that right now but
in a nutshell that's basically what
we're looking for we're looking to keep
that exposure time down so if there's
any vibration or drift or anything
that'll find its way into that
holographic setup during that exposure
time is eliminated
our next email question States I would
like to know if we can use the air as
the exhibition medium for showing
animated or single frame holography as
we see ads on electronic boards and the
person goes what goes on to say I am an
animator on PC working as a designer of
ads on electronic boards
I don't think this would fall under the
category of holography I I do think
there's a number of different
technologies that are creating things
similar to this I believe but I'm not
absolutely certain because this is this
is not my line here
that it's possible to take two laser
beams from very powerful lasers and each
laser being by themselves does not have
any effect on the air but were those
laser beams meet if they cross one
another the combination of the power of
those two beams causes the air right at
that spot to Glow So in theory if you
take those beams and control them using
a scanner and have them cross each
other's path in the air
each of those spots where those laser
beams touch one another and their powers
are combined you will get a glow
and you can draw out your images in that
way I'm also familiar with taking lasers
and scanning them inside of
photorefractive crystals though I
understand the crystals are relatively
small maybe only a few centimeters in
size and where those two laser beams
meet inside the photorefractive crystal
you also have the same effect that you
do in the air so no this isn't
holography that you're talking about
but I'm sure you know there's millions
of ways of doing three-dimension and
probably not Millions but there's a lot
of different ways to create
three-dimensional images that don't have
anything at all to do with holography
and this just happens
okay we're going to be covering the new
light craft vehicle and I have an
article about this new technology which
I would like to share with listeners I
also have a movie of this and I'll give
you the URL where you can find it in
just a minute but first let's learn a
little bit more about light craft itself
futuristic concept of a small
laser-propelled spacecraft has taken its
first research flights towards reaching
space
that progress has been measured by short
flights of 2 to 20 seconds duration at a
military research facility using a
high-powered infrared carbon dioxide
laser a wavelength invisible to the
naked eye
the achievement can be likened to Robert
goddard's first successful flights of
his liquid propellant chemical rocket
that attain a height of 41 feet after a
two and a half second burn in March of
1926.
sharp contrast with goddard's rockets
there is absolutely no fuel on board
this prototype laser boosted crafts
which has a diameter of 15 centimeters
mass of 40 to 50 grams machined from a
solid block of
6061-t6 aluminum
the Air Force research laboratory's
propulsion directorate at Edwards Air
Force Base California is conducting
these technology development research
and flight demonstrations additional
research money has been provided this
year by NASA's Marshall State flight
center Advanced space Transportation
program the laser propelled flights take
place at the White Sands Missile Range
in New Mexico at the high energy laser
systems test facility
the light craft propulsion research
employs the pulse laser vulnerability
test system a 10 kilowatt laser built by
Atco Textron for the Army
plvts is the highest average power
pulsed carbon dioxide laser presently
operating in the United States
the laser-propelled vehicle called
lightcraft because it flies on a beam of
laser light is designed to harness the
energy of a laser beam and convert it
into propulsive thrust
a light craft received the kilojoule
Pulses from the plvts laser at a rate of
10 times per second upon the
concentrating mirror that forms its rear
section the function of this parabolic
mirror is to focus the pulse laser
energy into a ring-shaped absorption
propulsion chamber here the laser beam
is concentrated to extremely high
intensities sufficient to momentarily
burst the inlet air into a highly
luminous plasma
instantaneous pressures reaching tens of
atmospheres providing thrust
this air breathing pulse detonation
engine concept owes its Origins to the
German V1 buds bomb of World War II that
ran on aviation fuel
the original light Craft Concept was
designed as a single stage to orbit
spacecraft that would become a micro
satellite upon reaching orbit the
spacecraft lifts off in a laser
propelled air-breathing engine mode and
as it nears Mach 5 speed and 30
kilometers altitude shifts into a laser
propelled rocket mode the air-breathing
engine mode would develop quasi-steady
thrust by pulsing at hundreds to
thousands of times a second depending on
the Mach number and altitude flown along
the Boost trajectory into orbit
the rocket mode would use onboard
propellant in the form of liquid
hydrogen or nitrogen to convert and
expand the laser energy for propulsion
once the light craft had climbed above
the atmosphere
unlike goddard's rocket engine no
oxidizer is required the fdio study
showed that all launch to orbital
conditions for a laser-propelled vehicle
could be satisfied by a single
high-power ground-based laser with or
without the aid of a low altitude laser
relay mirror
laser boost capability has been
demonstrated at the White Sands facility
with lightcraft reaching 14 feet
vertically in two second gyroscopically
stabled free flights as well as 400 foot
horizontal guide wire flights lasting 10
to 20 seconds
the researchers plan to increase the
light craft free flight altitude by
moving the launch stand outside test
cell number three where the flights will
no longer be limited by the lab's
ceiling height
the near-term goal is to reach an
altitude of one kilometer in the next 18
months with the plvts laser
climb even higher as an example 10 to
100 kilometers or near the edge of space
will require reactivating the 150
kilowatt pulse driver CO2 laser now
stored in test cell 2. preparations are
underway to enlist this powerful
infrared laser that was developed at the
avco research laboratory in the
mid-1970s
the predominant reason for investigating
this laser launch concept is its
low-cost Simplicity and responsiveness
upon demand laser light craft and their
propulsion modes are a radical departure
from the chemically fueled Rockets used
today
successful this new energy beam
propulsion technology will supplement
rather than replace current manned and
unmanned launch systems
the approach holds great promise for
reducing the launch costs of
microsatellites by several orders of
magnitude less than today's chemical
fueled rocket technology
the evolution of ultra lightweight high
temperature materials dual mode laser
propulsion engines powerful lasers and
the opportunity to change science
fiction into scientific fact are the
driving forces behind this joint project
so there you have a quick rundown on
what this LightWave technology is all
about I think this is really cool stuff
the fact that these crafts can be
propelled into space using laser beams
that's just one of the coolest things I
think that's come down the pike in a
long time now I have a URL which I'd
like to give to you where I've taken one
of the movies from the the experimental
stages of this project and you can log
on and see for yourself how this
technology works now here's the catch
you're going to need Real Player 5.0 to
view this so if you don't have Real
Player 5.0 either number one get it or
number two don't bother going over to
the page because when you download it
you're not going to be able to play it
now I recorded this so that it's a high
bit rate I think I use like 300K
connection rate for this so if anyone
has like a 28 8 mode and 56k modem
what's going to happen is you're going
to download this movie first you're not
going to watch it as a streaming movie
because it will not stream into your
modem it's it's set for a higher rate so
I have it set up so that you'll download
the real video itself I think it runs
about 300K or something like that it's
not that big for a movie it's only six
seconds
download it and watch it and see for
yourself how this works it's one of the
coolest things here's the URL
it's www.holoworld.com
slash
light craft
dot HTML and I'll put a link on this on
the holotalk page as well and lightcraft
is one word l-i-g-h-t
-r-a-f-t dot HTML and you'll see a
little link there just click on the link
you'll download the movie okay integraf
has an announcement they've received the
final delivery from agfa
this is it folks once it's gone it's
gone
and here's what they have in stock if
you're interested you can email
infograph and here's the email address t
j e o n g at AOL.com that's t j e o n g
at
aol.com
here's what we have
AE 56 film 30 centimeter by 40
centimeter by 50 sheets five boxes
8e 75 film
30 centimeter by 40 centimeter eight
inch by 10 inch
4x5 inch film 100 sheets in a box
I guess they have quite a bit of this
they have their uh it says here small
quantities and parentheses
so the one on the five boxes above is
all they have on that with the 8056 the
rest I guess they have a big order
80 75 plates
30 by 40 centimeter
10 in a box there's 10 boxes
that's all they have left
eight by ten
inch plates there's 10 in a box they
have 20 boxes left that's it
and then they also have four by five
inch plates which come 20 in the Box
they don't have any listing down here is
how many they have so maybe they've got
a nice size order of that
they also say that the integraf has
established a distributorship with
slavish and is keeping stock
and if it's not in stock they can get
delivery in one month on the following
items of sizes two and a half by two and
a half inch four by five inch eight by
ten inch Thirty by forty centimeter
plates only other sizes can be quoted
here's what they have
uh
pfg-01 which is similar to act for 8075
g-03 which is red sensitive to twice the
resolution of 80 75.
fpf green sensitive
pfg-03c this is a panchromatic for full
color reflection Holograms
price per plates on all lights are
similar to prices on agfa so if you want
to get information on either what's left
with agfa or the new plates themselves
that email address again is t j e o n g
aol.com
okay that wraps it up for another week
folks I'm out of here next week's guest
is going to be Derek gallon of Royal
holographic Gallery in Canada so log on
and hear what Derek has to say we'll be
interviewing him
by phone here from the studio and He'll
Be Our Guest next week which is the 21st
of December so for myself
and Debbie Lee who has the week off
have a good weekend thanks for listening
to holotalk see you next week